hello I'm your host David Barnard and my
guest today is Reed deramus growth
product manager at substack prior to
joining subsec Reed helped grow
subscriptions at Hulu Crunchyroll and
HBO Max on the podcast I talked with
Reed about whether or not to increase
your price how to execute if you do and
why price increases often impact growth
more than retention
hey Reed thanks so much for joining me
on the podcast today thanks for having
me really excited to be here so I wanted
to have you on I have read a bunch of
your posts this year and anytime I read
a great post I think gosh more people
need to read this so I now with my
colleagues publish a sub club newsletter
so I've shared your posts I think in
three different newsletters and this
then I always think we're reading a
great post I wonder what else is behind
this like what would they say about this
situation that wasn't covered I said hey
I've got a podcast I figured I'd have
you on and we could talk through some of
your posts so we'll link to the posts
and your growth croissant blog in the
show notes so people can go follow along
if they want really great stuff we're
not going to like read the posts we're
not going to cover everything but I want
to kind of hit some of these major
topics so the most recent one you wrote
and I think is super applicable right
now that a lot of apps are thinking
should I increase my price and then if I
am going to increase my price how do I
do it and not get the backlash and
everything so I wanted to kick off
talking about that so let's just start
with should you raise your price well
thanks again for having me on and really
appreciate the kind words a lot of the
times like you'll write a newsletter
post and you don't know if it lands or
not so really appreciate you and
appreciate you sharing it the price one
was one that was timely because Spotify
which I've subscribed to for you know
the past decade is doing their first
price increase and I think they've kind
of made it through by now and there's a
lot of writing out there and it was
something that we wrestled with a lot in
the streaming world because it's like
one of the most impactful ways to drive
up customer lifetime value and drive up
Revenue but there's this really hard
balancing act with executing a price
increase well and the trade-offs are
usually like
how much near-term revenue gain can I
try to capture and without sacrificing
your long-term growth potential because
if you go too hard into the price
increase you may get a lot of Revenue
early on but it could kind of erode your
growth velocity one specific metric to
think about is your year-over-year
growth in paid subscribers that's the
one that you kind of want to pay
attention to after you do these price
increases and yeah we can go a lot of
different ways from there but I'm
actually curious to get your take on
Disney plus and how this is played out
so they actually again announced a price
increase recently lambasted in the Press
worst time ever to do a price increase
everybody's complaining about Disney
plus quality going downhill but it's
interesting because they actually
started at five dollars and that kind of
what you were saying and what you talk
about in the post about growth versus
profitability
starting at five dollars is probably a
big reason why they grew so big so quick
it was just a no-brainer cheap decision
for a lot of families and people to
stream but now they're at that phase
where okay growth is over where's
Revenue growth going to come from more
price raises so do you think Disney plus
got it right even with the backlash
they're getting today in raising their
prices Now versus maybe having charged
more early on and it wasn't just Disney
plus I think when we were at Crunchyroll
even Hulu too the primary metric was
paid subscribers and baked into that was
this assumption that over time you could
gradually increase price I think Disney
launched at a really low price point and
a lot of people were getting Disney Plus
for free as part of Verizon they had
like a pretty big partnership with them
they had really discounted annual plans
at launch if I remember correctly and of
course they bundled it with ESPN plus
and Hulu which I think a lot of people
bought that as well so when Disney Plus
launch there was a lot of oh my gosh
they got to like 100 million subscribers
so quickly but you gotta like dig into
the numbers there and look at Revenue
per subscriber and really try to figure
out are they actually catching up with
Netflix or are they still pretty far
behind
and I think if you looked under the
covers the revenue per subscription
wasn't quite there whether they're doing
the right thing now it's what they have
to do like if you look at the streaming
space probably right now it's not the
easiest space to be operating in it's
been fascinating over the past decade
watching a lot of these traditional
media companies try to move from cable
TV into streaming video where the skill
sets needed to grow those products are
very different you have to like think
about direct to Consumer relationships
and how to grow subscribers that way
versus doing carrier deals with a
handful or more paid TV operators
totally different skill set and the
economics are really different so I
think it's been kind of a wild west and
there's a lot of volatility right now
there's a lot of M A I think that
consolidation will continue whether they
handled it right or not I don't really
know and I don't know if it really
matters I think they're doing what they
kind of have to do at this point a lot
of other streamers too in that is kind
of and you talk about this in your post
is that you will get some level of
pushback and I mean anytime somebody has
to pay more for what they perceive to
already be getting there is going to be
pushback I'm a father of four kids and
inflation's hitting pretty hard I mean
I'm getting a little more sympathetic to
maybe always raising prices isn't the
best idea how do you think about the
consumer sentiment part of the decision
of whether to raise prices or not well
one thing you mentioned there that I
think is important is if you're asking
them to pay more for what they perceive
as the same product it's a tough sell
maybe a marginal price increase will go
through okay like a one dollar price
increase two dollar price increase that
seems to be kind of the standard set by
Spotify and Netflix each time they raise
price they're not doubling their price
in one swing they're kind of marginally
going up the thing that we've seen
consumer products do well when they're
doing a price increase is reaffirm the
value prop that people are paying for
and you can also tease any upcoming
changes that would like materially
improve the product the value prop and I
think that can really help get you
through these price increases and so I
think Communications are really really
important and one of the things you
mentioned in the post too was actually
not just teasing future features but
maybe trying to coordinate the launch of
a big new feature with the price
increase like how would you pull that
off exactly like if you were Disney and
you had like some huge Star Wars series
in the pipeline
I would try to time the price increase
roughly around when those shows are
going to Premiere and you could say in
the comms this is what we're doing with
we're not just asking you for more money
for the sake of it and don't blame a
price increase on like inflation or
something that consumers can't control
that's kind of like one of those
uncontrollable factors like cost of gas
is going up sorry we got to increase our
price it's usually best to focus on your
product and how it's getting better and
how you're going to use this extra money
to continue to make the product better
and keep in mind the people who are
paying for it already definitely value
your product in some way so they're
going to be usually thrilled with that
idea of you trying to make a concerted
effort to continue to improve the thing
Disney I think actually did really well
maybe is that the time the Press
announcement before too big Series so
Ahsoka was just released this week as
we're recording and then they have a big
Marvel show coming out I think in the
next three or four weeks
so they announced it two or three weeks
ahead of that they don't go into effect
until mid series with these big new
shows and so it kind of did what you're
suggesting and they took the pr lumps
ahead and now people are excited again
because these big shows are coming on
and by the time the price increase
actually takes effect they're going to
be mid-show on these exciting new shows
that I think Disney had a lot of
confidence that we're gonna be very
attractive to their subscribers that's
exactly right I mean that's the best way
to do it like if your Spotify you don't
want to lose major podcasts or Led
Zeppelin or the Beatles catalog right
before you do a price increase the
timing piece is really important the
communication is really important so
we've been talking about huge players
Disney Spotify a dollar increase in
Spotify you know at this point most
people listen to music the way they
listen to music is streaming so there's
not really that much question of like am
I going to cancel Spotify it's me maybe
more am I going to switch from Spotify
to Apple music it's only really two or
three big players out there I mean what
do you think and have you done much
thought on these smaller subscription
apps where they don't have the brand
name they don't necessarily have they'll
kind of default people are going to
stick around are there any tips in how a
smaller app should think about a price
increase let me bring it into like the
sub stack world because these are
effectively all their own subscription
media business oh yeah yeah yeah and one
thing that we've talked with writers
about sometimes we'll do these reviews
you know and we'll go in and we'll look
at their retention metrics their growth
rate all these metrics to evaluate the
health of their business and sometimes
we'll say hey your paid retention rates
are like through the roof they're
incredible they're way better than your
peers and what we'll usually see is
they're like hell yeah and then just
totally tune out and feel reassured but
there's a flip side to that which is
that can also mean that your product is
underpriced or that you're not being
aggressive enough trying to grow your
audience and so the phrase that we try
to hammer home is your health metrics
are too good you know it's like going
into the doctor's office and they're
like look you need to like eat a
cheeseburger or something I think that's
actually one thing I see a lot of
writers on South stack that I think are
underpriced and they're not realizing
their full earnings potential in part
because they set their price a long time
ago it's a hard intimidating decision
and after you make that decision you
don't really want to think about it
again so you just see a lot of prices
kind of not changed even over the course
of multiple years
and I feel like they're not realizing
their full earnings potential that's a
great way to think about it because if
in our consumer subscription app world
that we mostly talk about here on the
podcast if you're seeing way above
median retention rates if you're seeing
way above median conversion to
subscription rates that might actually
be the sign that you're leaving money on
the table but then on the flip side if
you're seeing 20 retention which at
Revenue cap we shared a state of
subscription apps report where median
retention first consumer subscription
app on an annual plan is somewhere in
the 30 range so there's a lot of apps
that have way lower than that but then
there's also a lot of apps that have way
higher retention but if you're in that
20 retention on your annual
subscriptions probably signal that
you're not in a good place to raise
prices on your existing subscribers and
really thought about kind of looking at
those sorts of metrics as part of the
decision process and whether to raise a
price or not we see some writers on
substack retaining 90 of their
subscribers after one year which to me
is just like totally Bonkers yeah um and
I want to give a shout out to antenna
which is like a data product that really
looks at retention for the streamers
and they have some really great
retention data if you are operating like
a bigger consumer subscription product
that can be a good source of information
to compare and contrast it's obviously
awesome if your retention is above your
peers or above normal that's great news
but I too often see people put their
feet on the table and be like nice let's
Let It cruise I think it's good to think
about well maybe we are leaving some
money on the table maybe we're a little
underpriced so and then that's actually
the next thing I wanted to get into is
like how do you model out whether or not
you are leaving money on the table and
then how do you think about the
potential for churn when you do raise
your price I mean I can't show Excel
spreadsheets in a podcast but I mean
talk me through kind of the high level
thinking of how to drop that into a data
warehouse or a spreadsheet or how do you
model this out to see if it's really
worth it in the long run are you
sacrificing growth in the short term are
you sacrifice retention in the long run
I mean there's a lot of factors here the
easiest Avenues to break it out at the
highest level is to think about your
existing subscribers let's assume you're
adjusting the price for your existing
subscribers a lot of people when they do
a price increase they only do it for new
subscribers in the future and that's a
fine approach but just know that you're
leaving the vast majority of the impact
from a price increase on the table to
really realize the revenue gain from a
price increase it's important to figure
out a way to increase price for existing
subscribers I would caveat that to say
if you're really early in your journey
and there's not that many subscribers
that's the best time to just grandfather
people in and not piss people off not
mess with your churn like later stages
when that's maybe most applicable but
that's part of the calculation right
like how many existing subscribers do I
have and if I raise price on all of them
is it actually meaningful revenue and
worth doing and that's a great Point
keep in mind too the people who you're
talking about in that early stage are
people who are your founding members I
remember the first person who paid for
my newsletter I'm like you're God's gift
to Earth you know like thank you so much
I would Happily Never increase their
price that's an important Dimension to
think about your early supporters and to
make sure you're taking care of them but
yeah I think at a certain point if
you're at like a Netflix scale or a
Spotify scale even Strava Duolingo you
have probably enough paid subscribers at
that point to think about most of the
value of a price increase coming from
your existing subscribers if you assume
we're kind of in that world it's good to
break out the impact by the revenue gain
from existing subscribers versus future
flow of new subscribers coming in what
we typically see when we've done price
increases in the past is that they
usually impact subscriber acquisition
way more than subscriber retention now
that's assuming you kind of execute the
price increase well and that you're not
going bonkers with it you're not
doubling your price you know you're
doing the more incremental approach
but usually if you execute well you
won't see much churn from your existing
subscriber base but you will see a
little pressure on new subscriber
acquisition so say you're adding 100 000
new subscribers per month and you
increase the price by 10 it's not crazy
to see like a little bit of a step
function drop down you know maybe 90 000
a month or eighty thousand a month just
kind of pulling Money numbers out of
thin air here but the point being the
expectation should be that you're going
to see a little bit of slowdown on
acquisition whereas retention you might
not see too much of an impact and again
that's why it's important to like figure
out a way to thoughtfully increase price
on existing subscribers the basic
equation is like do you want fewer
subscribers paying you more money or do
you want more subscribers paying you
less money and then there's really a
very few who can achieve the kind of
more more subscribers paying you more
money it does happen one of the things a
Spotify and a Disney plus and others
can't do because they are such a big
brand is actually test the price
increase on new users before they
actually raise a price on existing users
and maybe that's actually a great way to
think about it for apps that can get
away with that if you're not a brand
name if people don't know your price
offhand if the Press isn't going to
write about your price then you can
actually go ahead and see first what the
impact is on new subscribers and then if
you find that sweet spot maybe that's
the time to then start thinking about
rolling that price out to all the
existing subscribers yeah there's a lot
of different ways to go about it testing
price increases is really hard if one
person sees two different prices and
they kind of figure out what you're
doing that can make its way to X or
Reddit and then you got a thing to deal
with but yeah I mean any kind of signal
there can be helpful surveys can
sometimes be somewhat helpful but people
say different things than what they end
up doing so I wouldn't put all your
trust in those results in those cases
where you have race prices in the past
have you done surveys is there kind of
like price elasticity surveying that
you've done and was it helpful or do you
feel like you really just have to
experiment we've definitely done a lot
of surveys and not only to find like
what our core price should be but to
think about what our most passionate
fans would pay relative to like your
core subscriber it's kind of like you
want to separate out what the top one
percent are willing to pay they maybe
have more price elasticity or a higher
willingness to pay a higher price for
maybe not even that much different of a
product relative to like your core
product which is what most people are
buying the equivalent on substack would
be we have a founding member tier and if
people choose that option they can
actually fill in their own price
and we see a lot of people go way above
and beyond what the retail price is on
the founding member and some of those
people just really want to support the
writer that's great to see yeah I was
actually going to bring that up that one
other option and we even see this in
streaming and Spotify and others is that
one way to raise your price without
raising your price is to add a higher
tier so we were talking earlier about
adding a big new feature at the same
time you're raising your price well
another way to potentially do that is
add that big new feature as a new
premium tier on top of the existing
tiers I wonder if that's actually a
better option than raising your price
for some apps is actually starting to do
the tiering thing do you have any
thoughts there in the I mean the problem
with hearing is complexity is that how
many prices are you showing your paywall
gets confusing what are your thoughts on
tiering as a way to raise prices I think
tiers make a ton of sense you know
without them you're kind of forcing one
price on everybody when you know that
people have different willingness to pay
I think it's good to keep it as simple
as possible more than three tiers the
consumer's brain might start to break
the other thing that we're seeing in
streaming is the introduction of AD
based subscription tiers at the lower
end I think a lot of this is just
reaffirming your point around you're
trying to think about how many paid
subscribers you can realistically get
and what the revenue per subscriber is
and how they break that out across
different tiers subscription tiers and
so if you're somebody like Netflix in
the US and you're really bumping up
against what could be your total
addressable Market
then introducing a lower price ad tier
could make sense same thing with the
other streamers what we see in more of a
passion driven world like the sub stacks
of the world or the patreons of the
world there's this element of like the
top one percent of fans who have like a
much stronger set of feelings about
their subscription to a certain product
we saw this at Crunchyroll we had this
thing called the T-shirt test which was
like if you wear the T-shirt of that
brand then it's saying something about
who you are about your identity and when
you see somebody else wearing that
Crunchyroll t-shirt you have this
immediate connection this immediate
trust and it's a great symbol for the
depth of relationship somebody feels
about a brand and so yeah not all
subscriptions are created equal and so I
think something like Crunchyroll
probably has a better shot at like a
higher priced subscription tier that has
some other stuff in it whereas Netflix
as high as priced here is more like a
family plan it's a functional value prop
I think that point you just brought up
about Netflix hitting their potential
total addressable Market in the U.S
it's actually something a lot of apps
are maybe hitting and not quite
realizing what wall they're hitting I've
heard a lot of folks in the industry say
for everything from fitness apps to
other apps in the space that you hit
this 10 to 20 million a year ARR and
very few apps can break beyond that and
maybe that's that you know you're not
Netflix you're not going to have 100
million subscribers or whatever it is so
these apps may be hitting that total
serviceable market like yes everybody
works out but realistically your fitness
app is not going to be subscribed
there's so much competition in that
space people have so many different
needs once you hit that 10 20 million
dollars a year you might actually be
bumping up against it and so then that's
the time to then start thinking okay
what are these tiers how do we start
letting people who are willing to pay
more pay more you know visco is an app I
use all the time and they raise prices
and I still think it's cheap because
it's like that's just where I go when I
have a photo I really like I've been
using the fitbod app and it's just been
so perfect for my at-home workouts and
it's 60 bucks a year I've paid trainers
60 bucks an hour to come train me I
would pay so much more because of how
well that product is fitting my needs so
yeah I wonder if that total serviceable
Market is what some apps are starting to
bump up against and need to start
looking at how these bigger players are
starting to diversify income streams I
think that's exactly right it's hard to
know when you're bumping up against that
ceiling the question we always got hit
with at Crunchyroll was like how many
people will actually pay for an anime
only streaming service when we got there
we had 200 000 subs and I remember us
being so skeptical of Ever Getting
Beyond where we were the idea of getting
to a million mind-blowingly hard
there was weeks where we would lose like
a thousand Subs you know or really slow
inching along pacing and we just kept
getting that question like how many
people will actually pay for this fast
forward to today and I think there are
over 12 million paid subscribers and we
didn't increase price for a long time we
really wanted to exhaust all the
possible ways of bringing on new
subscribers not to mention like we tried
to launch other products that were like
solving tangential needs for people who
were canceling Crunchyroll so we tried a
bunch of different things and only got
to a price increase pretty deep into my
time there you know after six or seven
years of really focusing on paid
subscribers and scaling that up as much
as possible
um honestly shocked in that Crunchyroll
to get to 12 million subscribers I think
there are maybe like two things going on
simultaneously here and I want to hear
one about how you at Crunchyroll started
to solve this and found new ways to grow
and expanded that audience but I think
there's a second thing at play here here
that it's kind of the rising tide lifts
all boats that consumers are more and
more willing to pay via subscriptions
for things they care about for things
they value and yes there is subscription
fatigue people complain about how many
subscriptions they have but then look at
the industry it's growing because when
you deliver value people are willing to
pay so I think I wonder if some of
crunchyroll's growth was part of that
Rising tide but then I'm sure y'all must
have done a lot of work so tell me about
what it took to get from those tens of
thousands of subscribers and not even
believing you could hit a million to 12
million subscribers which is just
incredible I mean we could talk for a
full day give me the highlights give me
the highlights so the highest level we
thought a lot about how do we acquire
more subscribers how do we retain our
existing subscribers there's a lot of
sub bullets in both of those we did a
lot of marketing stuff a lot of
partnership stuff and those were really
important but at the end of the day
what's the most important was like what
shows we had on on the service and then
we tried to build a strong brand around
that and back to the T-shirt thing it
wasn't always about building the best
video player or the best payments engine
or the best website or apps
we were able to compete on kind of a
different dimension because of the
deeper relationship we had with our
audience and so we thought a lot about
how do we build out a business around
our subscribers and introduce other
revenue streams like merch and events
and gaming and a bunch of different
things
and so that was useful because we didn't
have to like have the best video player
in line with Netflix or Amazon Prime of
the world but one of the things you
mentioned there is expanding shows so
ultimately and you talk about this in a
lot of your blog posts including the
price increase is that ultimately the
amount of money you're going to be able
to charge and the revenue you're going
to get per customer just really boils
down to how much value you're delivering
so it sounds like a lot of that growth
had to do with just how do we deliver
more and more and more value that's
exactly right and I know that's like
opaque and flippant to say but it really
is all that matters and so what do you
do from that you got to really figure
out why people are buying your product
and try to double down as much as
possible on that but the hard part is
you also got to keep an eye on why some
of your audience is canceling and
whether you can start trying to solve
some of their problems and gradually
expand from your core of your subscriber
base one of example from Crunchyroll
when we got there most of the people who
were paid subscribers for control at
that time were the most hardcore anime
fans in the world and we had to adjust
how we welcomed new anime fans
and that's like a branding and Vibe
thing and that showed up in some of the
marketing stuff we did but that was a
big change and honestly it took a little
bit of a change within the company from
a cultural perspective because the
company was all die hard anime fans and
so yeah I think there is mechanics like
that to be mindful of and to think about
like okay I need to figure out the value
that my existing subscribers are getting
I need to make sure I'm reinforcing that
but I also need to be mindful of how to
slowly expand from my core audience
today too if I want to continue driving
subscriber growth how do you figure that
out I mean you actually talk about this
in several other posts but let's talk
through aspects of that you survey your
users you product analytics how did
y'all figure out who those core users
were and what kept them and then how did
you figure out what those lighter users
who they were and then how to kind of
bring them deeper into the Crunchyroll
experience surveys are crucial and
there's different ways to do that you
could do like live interviews pick up
the phone talk to some of your most
passionate longest tenured subscribers
figure out why they have been around for
a while
you could talk to people who are
canceling like right away and try to get
a sense of what's the difference here
one easy analysis we did pretty
consistently in the streaming world was
this was back when free trials were a
thing you could do it with like the
First Billing month as well but look at
the people who are canceling their
subscription early on
look at the people who are making it
through that period and look for the
behavior that is different about those
two groups and try to figure out early
on what is indicative of risky Behavior
what is signaling valuable Behavior try
to bend the product in those directions
that onboarding period is like the most
crucial part of a subscriber journey and
that could be the first day the first
app session or the first month that
somebody's using your product
that's usually the place to focus if
you're really trying to like figure out
why people are getting value from what
you're providing and trying to figure
out how to like bend the product more
toward that direction that's a more
objective data analysis exercise but
yeah I would definitely do the surveys
and you could do that as part of
onboarding or just kind of ad hoc to
your whole audience and there's
different flavors of that you could just
send them like a Google form or you
could literally hop on a zoom and talk
to some people and really dig into what
they value and what they would like to
see from your product so for the people
who are canceling how do you really suss
out like there's cohorts that are just
never going to subscribe so there's I
think you say one of your posters three
buckets it's like the people who
subscribe and say subscribe the people
who cancel but you actually have
potential with them and they have the
people who are just not worth chasing
but how do you figure out who is who and
then especially I think a lot of people
will be thinking okay the people who
cancel but are actually winnable people
how do you suss out what's actually
going to be valuable enough to keep them
subscribed and go after that market yeah
there's like gradients here I guess
there's some people who maybe try your
product and they ask for something
that's totally abstract totally
different than what you're trying to do
in a lot of those cases I think you just
gotta say okay well thanks for coming by
we'll see you later then there are
people who are asking for things that
are not totally different than what
you're doing today for example with
Crunchyroll we'd get a lot of requests
for like popular shows or shows that
were kind of under the radar that we
could reasonably try to go get and we go
try to get it if we got it we'd email
them and say hey this is now on the
service you want to come back and maybe
potentially offer some kind of discount
to come back or trial period it's kind
of an intuition thing I think most
operators will probably be able to suss
out okay this person just probably
accidentally signed up or totally
misunderstood our value prop before they
signed up yeah this person's pretty
close and I think we could win them back
if we just made some slight adjustments
or slightly bent our product in this
direction it's fascinating too in the
consumer space just how big the numbers
can be is that if you have product
Market fit adjacency where people are
coming in for some reason but you're
just not quite solving their problem if
you figure that out and go from 10 20
trial start rate to 25 30 trial start
rate it can just make such a dramatic
difference in your business and it's not
like growth hacking your paywall you
have to actually deliver the value you
actually have to figure out what they
need and solve those problems it feels
like there's just so many competing
things there like how much effort you
put into new features how much you're
testing your paywall how much you're
offering discounts there's just so many
things to be thinking about I mean the
thing about writing the newsletter has
been this is all just like a balancing
act and it just takes High judgment
decision making there's no Universal
right answer to balancing between all
these pieces right I think it's like
getting a strong sense of your business
and like what is driving Revenue growth
and then being mindful when things start
ticking in different directions one
thing that we talked a lot about in the
streaming world it's like this pendulum
swinging between different business
priorities and growth and profitability
and all these counter forces and you're
always just trying to like fine tune and
tweak things and choose the right path
but it's all a balancing act and there's
no Universal right answer and that's why
it's been fun to write about the
Frameworks because I'm just trying to
write out the constructs of how we made
certain really hard but important
decisions and one of the things you keep
coming back to and a lot of your posts
is that it really does depend on stage
like if you're kind of early and
pre-product Market fit maybe don't worry
as much about returning which is kind of
like counter advice to what a lot of
people would expect like oh you need to
solve the Leaky bucket first through all
these retention tactics and win back
campaigns and all that
but when you're early probably better to
keep focus on product it's interesting
how you end up in these Frameworks
talking about the context around those
different kind of growth stages when
your pre-product Market fit you should
really just be focused on trying to
really find The Sweet Spot of what you
want to do and the product you want to
build and an audience you should not be
really worried about what your cancel
flow looks like or overthinking price
it's really about a Relentless focus on
finding product Market fit and I know
that's like another opaque phrase but
that's all that really matters early on
and so one of the risks I have with
writing the newsletter is there's a
bunch of I think early stage writers on
substack reading it and I really don't
want them thinking about running paid
ads out of the gate or thinking about
how to better retain long-term
subscribers it's a total different set
of priorities and it's about just
finding that initial traction which is
extremely difficult yeah interestingly
though in one of your posts you do kind
of mention that when retention is super
low it might actually be time to just
completely rethink things so I mean it's
going to vary business to business and
Netflix looks way different than the
kind of like I was talking about the
media and subscription app does have
fairly low retention but yeah how do you
decide you know is retention reasonable
and there's a path to more value or is
it just so low you need to like rethink
things yeah if you have like a bunch of
people downloading your app using it
once and never using it again I think
you don't have product Market fit at
that point it doesn't even have to be
that extreme if they use it three times
in the first week but then never come
back that could work for some consumer
products but for most probably not so I
think retention is a part of evaluating
whether or not you have found traction
but I don't think it's worth thinking
too hard about don't beat yourself up
about like some of the retention stuff
that we've written about especially
those growth tactics you know it's like
offering discounts in the cancel flow or
trying to solve the problem in the
cancel flow yeah there's different
growthy tactics which are really aimed
at catching people on the fence about
canceling before they actually cancel I
would put all that stuff out in the
future after you have enough subscribers
for that to be meaningful yeah and
that's a good point too I mean I hadn't
thought about it quite this way but it's
like early on your product should be
what retains not growth hacks like if
you're having to work so hard on
subscriber life cycle marketing and
doing all these win back campaigns and
offering discounts then that's actually
probably a sign that you need to double
down and figure out what's wrong with
the product that the product the value
you're actually delivering is not what's
retaining them yeah exactly all right
Reed we could talk for four more hours
and maybe I'll have you back on at some
point to talk through like 10 more blog
posts because they're all so good we've
got through like kind of one and a half
or one in two quarters but it was so fun
and we'll link to all these blog posts
that we mentioned and growth croissant
but anything else you want to share as
we're wrapping up no this was awesome I
would love to come back thank you for
sharing the newsletter and thanks for
having me on it's been a blast
[Music]
thanks so much for listening
if you have a minute please leave a
review in your favorite podcast player
you can also stop by
chat.subplub.com to join our private
community
[Music]